PROFESSOR: So why do we
want agents that plan?
Well, think about it.
You're building an agent.
Let's say, you have an agent like the
one from last time, that's trying to
get an apple off of a tree.
Well, you could write down code that
says, if detect apple, then move
towards apple.
Right.
Or this could be a Pac-Man playing
agent, where you say, if
next to dot, eat dot.
If near ghost, run away from ghost.
And if you try to write down a simple
function which maps directly from what
you observe to what you do, turns out
that you can make bad decisions.
It's very hard to write these agents.
And then, they do something
crazy, right.
You move towards the apple.
And it turns out, moving towards
the apple is not such a bad
rule of thumb, right.
In general, that's how you get apples.
In some contexts, it's a bad idea.
And in order to know it's a bad idea,
you either have to write a
ridiculously complex function that says,
if apple and not cliff and blah,
blah, blah, blah, then jump.
Or what you can do is, instead, have a
much more simple and elegant system,
which considers that that's a bad idea,
considers the alternative, and
comes to the conclusion that some other
plan that may be more complex--
it may take several steps
to achieve your goals--
still achieves them in a better way.
So we'd like to be able to write agents
like the one on the right, that
plan ahead and are therefore able to
do the contextually appropriate
action, where you don't have to write
down the very complicated relationship
between the context and the action.
Instead, that should come
out of your model.
That's the key idea here.
So on one hand, the first kind of
agent, where you just write,
basically, if-then statements.
Where you say, if you
see this, do this.
That's technically called
a Reflex Agent.
A Reflex Agent is an agent whose
action is chosen based
on the current percept.
So you see the apple.
Or you see the dot.
Or you see the ghost.
And based on what you're perceiving
right now, you basically have some
kind of lookup table.
And you do your thing.
There's a direct and relatively simple,
in the sense of computation,
mapping between inputs and actions.
Now, it could be complex.
And that lookup table could
be very, very big.
Reflex agents are entirely allowed to
have memory or a model of the world's
current state.
So there may be things you can't see.
And you're keeping track of what
you've done in the past.
You can have state and still
be a Reflex Agent.
Reflex Agents refer to the fact that
you don't consider the future
consequence of your actions.
Instead, you only consider how
the world is right now.
And how the world is may
relate to your memory.
But you don't consider the future.
So there's this question.
Can a reflex agent actually
be a rational agent?
Why are we even talking
about these things?
Aside from the fact, that if you just
sat down before this class to write an
agent function, you'd probably
write a Reflex Agent.
Well, let's see some demos.
Here is a Reflex Agent for
the game of Pac-Man.
Its program is, if you are
next to a dot, eat it.
Or more generally, move towards
the closest dot.
OK.
Now, if I execute it, it will,
in a beautiful, rational
way, clear the board.
You can think ahead all you like.
You've still got to go around the
circle and eat all the dots, in
basically that way.
So in this case, reflex
can be rational.
It can also have problems.
So let's take a look at a reflex agent,
in a slightly more complex
environment.
All right.
So it's going towards the
closest dot, until now.
OK, so what happened?
What went wrong here?
Well, what went wrong here is, in order
to step towards the closest dot,
you choose the action east.
That turns out to not
be very effective.
Once you take the action east, you're
back where you started.
And you do it all over again.
This is kind of classic Reflex
Agent shenanigans.
So Reflex Agents, we love them.
So back to the question,
can they be rational?
Of course, they can be rational.
Rationality is a function of the actions
you take, not the computation
that led to them.
So if you had a big enough, good enough
lookup table, and you're taking
the right actions.
Rationality doesn't care what
process led to them.
Reflex is a comment on
the thought process.
On the other side, you have Planning
Agents, which, by the way, could fail
to be rational, depending
on how they work.
A Planning Agent, unlike a Reflex
Agent, asks what if.
In order to make its decisions, it
thinks about what the consequences of
its actions will be.
Now, of course, one way to find out the
consequences of your actions is to
do them, to execute them
in the real world.
We'll come back to this point much
later, when we talk about
Reinforcement Learning.
But right now, a Planning Agent does
not actually figure out the
consequences of its actions
by doing them.
It doesn't realize that it's going
to fall off the cliff by
jumping off the cliff.
Instead, it computes the consequences
in simulation, in a model.
So in order to have a Planning Agent,
you must have a model of the world.
And instead of trying things in the
world and seeing their consequences,
you try them in the model and
find out their consequences.
Now that, of course, means that
you have to formulate a model.
And then, you also have to formulate
a notion of what you're trying to
achieve, within that model.
And that's going to be
called your goal.
Or in general, it'll be a goal test.
Because there may be a lot of
ways the world could be that
you'd be happy with.
Like you might want an apple, but
you don't care which apple.
The hallmark of a Planning Agent is that
it considers how the world would
be, if it did a certain thing.
Some ideas that are important here are
the distinction between optimal and
complete planning.
A complete Planning Agent finds
a solution, finds a way of
achieving its goals.
An optimal agent, instead, not only
finds a way to achieve its goals, but
also finds the best way, according
to some cost function.
So we'll constantly be talking, in this
lecture and the next, about a
distinction between being able to find
a solution versus being able to find
the best one, two different criteria.
In addition, a Planning Agent can either
be kind of entire Planning
Agent that comes up an entire
plan and then executes it.
Or it comes up with many plans,
one after the other.
The agent that comes up with many plans
and continues to re-plan is
called a Replanning Agent.
Let me show you the distinction
between these.
All right.
So here's a configuration again.
This is the one where the
Reflex Agent got stuck.
Remember, it got stuck in the
upper left hand corner.
And this is going to be
a Replanning Agent.
So it finds a path to a dot.
It doesn't care which one.
And then it executes that plan.
At which point, it will have
eaten at least one dot.
And then, it repeats that.
So it's going to do a bunch of plans, to
get a dot after a dot, after a dot.
And as a result, let's
see what it does.
You can see at the bottom, actually,
its thought process flashing by.
It's doing search after
search after search.
And you know, maybe not the most
efficient way, but sooner or later, it
gets all of the dots,
and lightning fast.
Here's a different agent.
This is the Mastermind Agent.
This is Mastermind Pac-Man.
This agent does not just come up with
a mini plan and then go off.
It sits, and it thinks.
And it thinks.
And it finds the best way to
clear all of the dots.
Its goal is not getting one step closer
to to clearing the board.
Its goal is to clear the entire board,
in an evil genius kind of way.
So let's see what it does.
Well, the most important thing
it does is it thinks.
So it's setting up its thinking.
It's not even thinking yet.
OK, now it's it's thinking.
It's doing something.
We're going to find out
today what it's doing.
It's still doing it.
And what it's doing is search.
And so it's expanding a lot of
nodes, thousands of nodes.
It's thinking very, very
deep thoughts.
Because this is, in fact,
a tricky problem.
And it's still thinking.
But now, when it finishes thinking,
behold the evil genius.
Not a millisecond of waste, it knows
to end with the dead end.
So it doesn't have to backtrack,
brilliant.